<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached in Christ's-church, Dublin, on the 23d of October, 1695 being the anniversary thanksgiving for putting an end to the Irish Rebellion, which broke out on that day, 1641 : before the House of Lords / by Henry Lord Bishop of Killaloo.</title>
            <author>Rider, Henry, d. 1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91815</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1441</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15253</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11848953</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11848953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">153296</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91815)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 153296)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 546:11 or 2358:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached in Christ's-church, Dublin, on the 23d of October, 1695 being the anniversary thanksgiving for putting an end to the Irish Rebellion, which broke out on that day, 1641 : before the House of Lords / by Henry Lord Bishop of Killaloo.</title>
                  <author>Rider, Henry, d. 1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by and for J. Ray ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Item at reel 2358:14 identified as Wing R2417A.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in Cambridge University Library and Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  Rebellion of 1641.</term>
               <term>Sermons --  England --  London --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:153296:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:153296:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Thurſday</hi> 24th of <hi>October,</hi> 1695.</head>
            <head type="sub">By the Lords Spiritual &amp; Temporal in Parliament Aſſembled.</head>
            <opener>ORDERED,</opener>
            <p>On motion, that the Earl of <hi>Mount-Alexander</hi> and the Lord Viſcount <hi>Charlemount</hi> do give the Thanks of this Houſe to the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Killaloo</hi> for his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached before this Houſe at <hi>Chriſt's-Church</hi> Yeſterday, being the Anniverſary of the Three and Twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> And that his Lordſhip be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to cauſe his Sermon to be Printed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Gerard Bor. Cler. Parliamentorum.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:153296:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED In CHRIST's-CHURCH, DUBLIN; On the 23d of <hi>October.</hi> 1695.</p>
            <p>Being the Anniverſary Thankſgiving for putting an End to the IRISH REBELLION, which broke out on that Day, 1641.</p>
            <p>BEFORE THE HOUSE of LORDS,</p>
            <p>By <hi>HENRY</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>KILLALOO.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DUBLIN, Printed by and for <hi>J. Ray,</hi> and are to be Sold by the Bookſellers in <hi>Dublin.</hi> 1695</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:153296:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:153296:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached on the 23d of <hi>October,</hi> 1695.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job, 8.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>The Hypocrite's Hope ſhall Periſh.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IT was the ſaying of a Great and Wiſe Man, that moſt of the Creatures are worthy of our beſt Thoughts, and deſerve our ſerious Obſervation: That ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is to be Learn'd from every one of them, as well from the ſmalleſt Inſect under our Feet, as from the glitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Canopy over our Heads; as well from the leaſt Atome in the Sun Beams, as from the Glorious Luſtre of the Moon and Stars. Naturaliſts tells us, That the Engle taught us Architecture, and drew the firſt Model of an handſom and convenient Houſe; That the Spider ſhew'd the Weaver the uſe of the Shuttle and the Loom, the good Houſewife to manage the Spindle and the Wheel; That Swallows were the firſt Profeſs'd Oculiſts; That the River-Horſe taught us how to breath a Vein, and that we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to ſeveral other Animals for many excellent Diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; both in Chirurgery and Phyſick: We find too many of the Creatures inſtructing us in things that more nearly do concern us, Reading Lectures to us, and Diſcourſing with us, like ſo many Profeſſors in Divinity: The Prophets direct us to the Stork, the Turtle and the Crane, to the Ox and to the Aſs, to learn us Gratitude, and our time of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning unto the Lord. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſends us to the Ant, to Preach to us Frugality and Thrift, and a Greater and Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer than <hi>Solomon,</hi> to the Serpent and the Dove for Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence and Wiſdom.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:153296:4"/>
            <p>Nay all the Trees, the Plants, and Flowers of the Field, from the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon</hi> to the Hyſſop that ſpringeth out of the Wall, are ſpoken of by the Holy Pen-Men, who condeſcending to our Capacities, borrow many handſom Alluſions from things, that we are intimately acquainted with, from the Vine and the Fig-Tree, the Thiſtle and the Thorn; and indeed from almoſt all the Herbs and Greens of the Earth.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Bildad</hi> introduces the Words Read unto you. Can the Ruſh grow without Mire? Can the Flag grow without Water? whilſt it is yet in its Greeneſs, and not cut down, it withereth before any other Herb, ſo are the Paths of all that forget God, and <hi>the Hypocrite's Hope ſhall Periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the Words we ſhall conſider,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Perſon, the Hypocrite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>What his Hopes are, and how he comes to Hope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>The End and Conſequence of his Hopes, they ſhall Periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed may be thought no very proper Subject for the occaſion; the Tragical Story of the day, the horrid Cruelties, Barbarous Murders, and unſpeakable Sufferings the poor Proteſtants groan'd under, might very well have been expected to have been fairly repreſented to our View: When <hi>Saul</hi>'s Sword againſt the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> ſeem'd to be drawn among us, and to act with that large Commiſſion, to ſlay both Man and Woman, Infant and Suckling, Ox and Sheep, Camel and Aſs, only with this difference, that our implacable Enemies ſpared not ſo much as the beſt of the Sheep and Oxen: When the mercileſs Perſecutors of our Fore-fathers, had not always ſo much goodneſs as to Kill, ſo much Humanity as utterly to deſtroy; But prolong'd their miſerable Lives, took care that they might linger under their Torments, and feel themſelves dye, and at laſt out of the abundance of their Compaſſion, diſpatch'd them with a Stab at their Hearts, and that dreadful Imprecation, <hi>Thy
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:153296:4"/>Soul to the Devil.</hi> When the Blood of the Innocent was ſhed like Water on every Side, Lamentations and Wailings were Echo'd from every Corner, and our weeping <hi>Rachils</hi> ſate bemoaning themſelves, and had none to comfort 'em: When the Cry in moſt Places was ſomething louder than that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> for there was ſcarce an Engliſh Family in which there was not more than one Dead; when the dead Bodies of Gods Servants that lay weltring in their own Gore were denied the common kindneſs of the Grave, and were given to be Meat unto the Fowls of the Air; and the fleſh of his Saints unto the Beaſts of the Field, and the moſt brutiſh fury of that bloody Crew was eſteem'd Meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious, and thought to deſerve not only the Encomiums of a Conclave, but the Apoſtolical Benediction. It may I ſay be expected, that I ſhould enlarge upon theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars; but hope that the Task may be equally ungrateful to us all; That as we delight not in the Effuſion of any Mans Blood, ſo we Sympathize too far with the Sufferings of our Anceſtors, to diſturb the weary that are at reſt, to lay open their Bleeding VVounds, to revive thoſe perſuaſive Calls to Revenge, thoſe Cries and fearful Screeches which run Parallel to nothing, but that in the Revelation; <hi>How long Lord, Holy and True, wilt thou not Judge and Avenge our Blood?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>VVe ſhall therefore proceed according to the Method laid down, and as we inſiſt upon the ſeveral parts of the Text, take ſome notice of the Hypocriſie and Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our falſe Brethren, ſhow you what their Hopes were, and that they alſo fell ſhort of all their Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then we ſhall conſider, the <hi>Perſon, the Hypocrite;</hi> the word Hypocrite in its Natural and Genuine Senſe, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies an Actor or a Player, one who upon the Publick Stage perſonates another, impoſes upon the Spectators, and paſles for the Man he only repreſents.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:153296:5"/>
            <p>And indeed as the Heathen long ſince obſerved, the whole VVorld is a Large Theatre, where the generality of Men do no more than decently repreſent the Perſons they would be thought to be; and the very beſt of them may put the ſame Queſtion to themſelves, that the Emperor <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> did to his Friends, when he lay a dying; have not I acted the play of Life very well. For they are diſguiſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a thouſand ſeveral ſhapes, are all mere ſhew, face, and appearance, and he that knows not how to act his part, to play the Hypocrite and Diſſembler, knows neither how to Rule nor to Obey; he will make but an awkard Monarch, a rough unaccompliſh'd Courtier, and in moſt Profeſſions, will want many of thoſe Qualifications, which uſually po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and recommend a Man, to the good opinion of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken World. But then the word Hypocrite, ſignifies a Religious Cheat, a Wolf in ſheeps cloathing, a Devil in the habit of a Saint, in the Garb of an Angel of Light, one who hath much the colour, but little of the ſubſtance, a great deal of the form, but ſcarce any thing of the power of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs; one whoſe beſt ſide is always outward, who makes it his buſineſs to be thought Religious, who labours not ſo much to be really good, as to appear unto Men to be ſo.</p>
            <p>And now to draw up the Curtain, and bring him upon the Stage; Firſt, Let us take a View of him at his Devotions. He enters into the place of publick Worſhip, with a ſolemn ſet Face. He perhaps proſtrates himſelf on the ground, zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly lifts up his hands and eyes towards Heaven, flaſhes and diſciplines himſelf after the manner of <hi>Baal's</hi> Prieſts, cries aloud, ſmites upon his Breſt, and makes a Profeſſion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing his Sins, with an humble, penitent and obedient heart.</p>
            <p>By the ſhew he makes, any Man would imagine, That he was above the trifling Things of this lower World, that his Soul was upon the Wing, and full of heavenly Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that he was talking with his God, as familiarly as ever <hi>Moſes</hi> did, even as a Man ſpeaketh to his Friend;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:153296:5"/>and yet all this while he is but acting a Part, mimicking the Saint, and giving a lively Repreſentation of an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Pious and Religious Man. For he is Proud, Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, and Diſobedient; God is not in ſo much as one of all his Thoughts; he draws nigh unto him only with his Lips, and thinks of every thing more than of Him; he then only pretends to Worſhip, and perhaps in his whole Life, never made a hearty Prayer, nor ſent up one ſincere Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the God and Father of all things.</p>
            <p>But to ſhift the Scene, ſometimes you may ſee the Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crite in his Penitential Dreſs, in a hair Shirt, in the habit of a Pilgrim; or in Sackcloath and Aſhes: At other times, you may obſerve him, hanging down his Head like a Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh, ſowring and disfiguring his Face, looking indeed like a Man that did afflict his Soul, mortifie his Members, and bring them into ſubjection to the Spirit; And yet theſe exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Severities are rarely attended, with any inward Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Heart; all the while he keeps his Body Low, Thin and Meager, he feeds his Old Sins, he pampers and every Day recruits his Inclinations to new Tranſgreſſions; in the midſt of all his abſtinence, his Soul has its ſecret Revels and Frolicks in Sin, he drinks Iniquity like Water, and acts all Uncleanneſs with Greedineſs,</p>
            <p>And as his Faſting is only acted, ſo are his deeds of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. When he beſtows his Alms, it is with all the outward Pomp and Solemnity that may be, in the Streets or in Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the greateſt Reſort and Concourſe; He proclaims the time of his Benevolence, <hi>to morrow I will give;</hi> He ſounds a Trumpet before his good Dees, ratling his Mony into the poor Man's Box; and reaches out his hand with ſuch a ſad Countenance, with ſuch an Air of Goodneſs and Compaſſion; as if he indeed felt their Wants; was their Brother and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion in Tribulation, and bore a part in all their Sufferings and Neceſſities; and yet the kindneſs is only deſigned to himſelf, and were it not to gratifie his vain glorious Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:153296:6"/>to get the Reputation of being pitiful and tender Hearted. Were all his Charitable Acts to be ſecret, and the World not to know, what either his right, or his left Hand did; they would be confin'd to a narrow compaſs, even end where they begin at home, and he would part with that Traſh his Money, as if it was indeed, what the Rabbins call it in their Language, <hi>his deareſt Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we look into the Hypocrit's Behaviour, in all other Caſes, you never find them, without their little Shifts and Devices, to ſecure their Credit, without ſome ſpecious pretences to palliate the blackeſt of their Crimes; I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſeveral particulars, but ſhall only name ſome few, relating to that Barbarous Rebellion in this Kingdom; and here the Popiſh Party tell us, they took up Arms in Defence of his Majeſty's Perſon and Royal Prerogative; whereas in deed thoſe great Pretenders to Loyalty, rais'd Armies, coyn'd Money, granted Letters of Repriſal, ſent Ambaſſadors to foreign Princes, invaded and rifled all the choiceſt and moſt valuable Jewels of the Crown.</p>
            <p>It was ſay they, A Juſt and Holy War, for the Liberty of their Conſciences, and the freedom of that which they call their Faith and Religion, and yet at that very time, they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd ſuch a licentious freedom of all their Superſtitions, that if one of their own holy Fathers may be credited, the Frogs in the ſecond Plague of <hi>Egypt</hi> were not more numerous, than the Prieſts and Fryers, that then ſwarm'd within the precincts of this one City; but it has never been thought any Reflection, either on the Piety, or Charity of the good Catholicks, to ſhelter their Pride and Ambition, their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice and Revenge, under the colour of Religion, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit Chriſt's Commiſſion, to put his Croſs into their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and to expreſs their Zeal for the Lord and his Houſe, in the Blaze and Flames of their Neighbours.</p>
            <p>But then alaſs! The Proteſtants were the firſt Aggreſſors, and the Papiſts not daring to ſtay at home, Aſſembled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:153296:6"/>purely for the ſafety of their Lives, and their mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual preſervation; and therefore admire that they ſhould be call'd Rebels, who were only a few diſcontented Gentlemen, apprehenſive of a general Maſſacre, and could not but make ſome little defence for themſelves, and civilly oppoſe them, who firſt blew the Trumpet, and were ready for the Battle.</p>
            <p>It would be endleſs to enumerate all the Pretences they made uſe of, for the advancing of their Cauſe, the frequent profeſſions of their kindneſs and affection to their Engliſh Neighbours, the deceitful Kiſſes, and treacherous Embraces they gave them, the Crocodiles Tears they ſhed over them, till they had got their Goods and Arms into their Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the Obliging Diſtinction they made for ſome days, between the Britiſh Inhabitants, till they had Complemented and Wheedled the Scotch too into the Snare, the breach of all their Articles, the Perfidious Violation of the moſt Sacred Oaths and Promiſes, and the many other little Arts and Pious Frauds, their Holy Church at that time eſpecially Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimated, to Decoy the credulous Proteſtants into their Nets, till they were miſerably betray'd, and baſely Butcher'd by thoſe they Truſted, upon the inſignificant Pledges, of their Word and Honour.</p>
            <p>Thus if you follow the Hypocrite thro' all the other parts of his Life, the beſt thing you can ſay of him is, that he is a good Actor, he treads the Stage handſomly, he pronounces his Words with a Grace, and ſpeaks his Part admirably well, he has the Garb, the Geſture and Countenance of a very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Man, of an Iſraelite indeed, in whom is no Guile, he looks like the Tombs and Monuments of the Dead, which are ſet off with a great deal of Coſt and Charge, appear Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, and make a goodly Shew, but within are full of dead Mens Bones, of Rottenneſs and Corruption; for he has not ſo much as one of thoſe good Qualities he pretends to; take him but into the tiring Room, ſtrip him, and lay aſide his Robes, pull off his Mask and Vizard, that Paint and Fucus,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:153296:7"/>which he lays on with ſo much Art and Cunning, he will then be ſeen as he is, a deform'd ſhrivel'd Piece, a miſerable Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle indeed; and yet for all that, he hopes he ſhall come off very well, and claps and applauds himſelf: And therefore in the next place we ſhall conſider, what grounds he has for his hopes, and from whence they do proceed.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then the Hypocrites Hopes may proceed from this; he has found by long experience, That his bare Pretences to Virtue, have ſerved his turn very well in this World, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted his Intereſt, and been as advantagious to him, as if it had been real: He has acquired it may be, a great Eſtate, Honours, and Preferments, by the appearance of being a good Man, got his Fathers Bleſſing by the ſmoothneſs of his Carriage, ſound Favour in the Eyes of his Prince, by Diſſimulation and Flattery, and with <hi>Abſolom,</hi> ſtollen the Hearts of all the People, by his fair Speeches; his courteous and obliging Behaviour, his Honeſty, ſuch as it is, as far as he knows, has never been Miſtruſted; and he hope ſtill to carry on the Cheat, to deceive Heaven, as well as he has done Man, and concludes, That the ſame Arts which have Enabled him to go beyond his Brother, may do him the like Service, in Over-Reaching and Abuſing of his God.</p>
            <p>He has been Bleſt with the Fat of the Earth, and the Dew of Heaven; the Sun has Shin'd as Warmly, and the Showers of Rain, Refreſh'd him as much, as the beſt of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; he proſpers in the World, and has Riches in Poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and he cannot but look upon ſuch Bleſſings, as an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of ſome future Favour. By the large ſhare he has of the things of this Life, he judges what proportion he may expect in the next, and from every lucky hit, ſtill draw this inference, That he who has been ſo Fortunate, and had ſo much Goods laid up for many years here, muſt have ſome Happineſs hereafter, at leaſt a Childs Portion in Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:153296:7"/>
            <p>But ſuppoſe the worſt; ſeeing the Tares grow together with the Wheat, he hopes that at the general Harveſt he may be thrown into the Barn among the other Sheaves; that the Counterfet may not be diſcern'd in ſo great a heap of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones; that the goodneſs of the Foyl may give it ſuch a Luſtre, that it may ſparkle even in the Eyes of God himſelf, and paſs without ſuſpition, when he comes to make up the faireſt of his Jewels.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The Hypocrite may hope upon this account. His conſtant endeavours have been to ſet himſelf handſomly off, to acquire all the outward viſible ſigns of Piety and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, without any regard to the inward purity of his Heart, and he has been ſo long uſed to diſſemble with others, that he has even forgot to deal honeſtly and ſincerely with himſelf.</p>
            <p>The fooliſh Actor, who was to perſonate a King, when he ſaw himſelf ſurrounded with Guards and Attendance, with all the pomp and ſolemnity of a Court, tho he had not one Royal Quality or Princely Virtue, nothing of that largeneſs of Soul, none of thoſe generous and noble Thoughts, which are abſolutely neceſſary to ſo conſiderable a Dignity, to ſo high a Calling: He began to fancy that he was born for ſome great Deſigns, that he was cut out for a Crown, and really was the mighty Perſon he repreſented. So our Religious Player, tho he has none of the qualifications of a Saint, nor any Truth in his inward Parts. Tho he is utterly a ſtranger to all the great Duties of Religion, and never heartily bewailed or truly repented of any of the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of his life, yet he has worn the Robes of Right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs ſo long, that from the colour of his Habit he judges of the cleanneſs of his Heart; from the whiteneſs of his Garments, that he has kept himſelf unſpotted from the World; and at laſt is given up to the ſtrongeſt of Deluſions, to believe himſelf, and concludes with the proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee, <hi>That he is not as other Men are;</hi> That God cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get to be gracious to him, but will accept his perſon, and receive him into his mercy and favour.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:153296:8"/>
            <p>Thirdly, The Hypocrite may hope, imagining that there is ſome recompenſe due, to the good Figure He has made in the World, and that there is ſomething of merit, even in his diſſimulation. Religion in his opinion gets ſome credit, by the reſpect Men only ſeem to pay it. It is one proof of his virtuous Inclinations, that he hides and conceals his Vices, and ſurely think He, the outward Expreſſions of Piety, the bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd diſguiſe of Devotion, has a better Title to forgiveneſs, than down right Atheiſm and Profaneſs; a counterfeit zeal for the ſervice of God, ſuch a one as <hi>Naaman</hi>'s in the houſe of <hi>Rim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> muſt be much leſs offenſive, than to kick at his Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, pollute his Sanctuary, and Convert that Holy Place, into an Houſe of Merchandize, a den of Thieves.</p>
            <p>For thus he may be willing to juſtifie and argue for Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: He conſtantly frequents the Church, no Man comes with more reverence and humility, or crys louder, Lord, Lord, than He doth, He faſts twice in the week, and makes little or no proviſion for the fleſh, He is nicely Exact in obſerving all the minuteſt circumſtances of the Law: had rather ſtarve than gather a few Sticks, rather periſh with Hunger than pluck a few Ears of Corn on the Sabbath Day; He gives Tythes of all that He poſſeſſes; It is a weighty matter, in his Opinion, to ſcruple the payment of ſo juſt a Debt, a robbing of God Himſelf; and He would not be guilty of Sacriledge, no not in that ſenſe, for all the World; He gives alms, and has lent conſiderable Sums unto the Lord, and believes He has put his Money into good hands: He never turns ſo much as his Face from any poor Man, and he truſts that the Face of the Lord, ſhall never be turned away from him.</p>
            <p>For his part, He cannot but think, he has contributed ſome thing to the honour of God, and the Intereſt of Religion; and could wiſh there were many more ſuch Hypocrites as he is; That all our Leopards would rather conceal their Spots, and our Ethiopians change their Skins, than that they ſhould publiſh their Tranſgreſſions, make their Crimes their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:153296:8"/>declares their Sins as <hi>Sodom,</hi> and Glory in their ſhame.</p>
            <p>Thus the Hypocrite, tho he has not liv'd up to the ſtricteſt Rules of our moſt holy Religion, nor made his Heart bend to the ſeverer Precepts of the Goſpel, yet for as much as his good deeds, have been tranſacted in the ſight o fall the People, and in the face of the Sun, and his bad ones in his ſecret chambers, or in thoſe darker receſſes of his Soul: That his life may have been exemplary, and the Copy taking, ſeeing no Man knows the defects of the Original; That he has brought as he vainly dreams, no blemiſh to his Profeſſion, nor done any publick diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to his God; Tho He cannot pretend to that great Reward, due to the ſincere, honeſt, and good Heart, to them that have born the heat and burden of the Day; yet he ſees no reaſon why he may not hope for his Penny in the Evening; why He may not gather up ſome of the crumbs that fall from his Maſters Table; why God may not diſpence with a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation, and accept the formality of holineſs, for real and ſubſtantial Vertue and Religion.</p>
            <p>Theſe may be ſome of the Reaſons, which the Hypocrite gives for the hoes that are in him, Theſe the Reeds on which He loans, the feeble props which ſhore up his tottering Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations; for after all the poor Apologies he can make for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, He is in a loſt and undone condition, he muſt be miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, he and all his hopes muſt Sink and Periſh together, and that for theſe following Reaſons.</p>
            <p>All he aim'd at, in the whole courſe of his Life, was to be popular, to inſinuate himſelf into the good eſteem, and to get the praiſe and commendation of Men, That was the recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence he principally had an Eye to, and having had that in ſo large a meaſure, he ought not to expect or hope for any other. Had the Cardinal as he too late conſider'd, ſerv'd his God, as faithfully as he did his Prince, He would never have caſt him off in his old Age, nor have forſaken him when he was Gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed. Had the Hypocrite courted the favour of Heaven.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:153296:9"/>with as much earneſtneſs, as he did the applauſe of the World, had he been as ambitious of the Glory of God, as of the fair Character of his fellow Servants, he might have enlarg'd his deſires, and promis'd himſelf; even all thoſe good things, which God hath prepared for them, that ſincerely love and truly fear Him: But ſeeing that all his good Works, were done upon no other account, but to be ſeen of Men that that was the Grand deſign and drift of all his actions, and that he made that his chief end, God has made it ſo too, he verily has had his reward, and muſt never look for more; he has had his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward: It is indeed, one of the moſt terrible Sentences in all the Scriptures, and as the Learned interpret, imports thus much, He has receiv'd all that was due unto him; he has gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven God a Diſcharge, ſubſcrib'd an Acquittance in full ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and can never in reaſon, or juſtice, demand and thing ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from him.</p>
            <p>But then again; The Hypocrites hopes muſt Periſh, for he provokes &amp; affronts God as much as the moſt leud and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fligate ſinner living He profeſſes a great reverence for him, it is part he tells you of his Creed, That God is preſent every where, that he ſearches the Heart, and darts his Eyes into every corner of his Soul, and yet he uſes him worſe then he would do the meaneſt Man, and ſecurely acts the greateſt Villanies, under his Eye, which he would tremble to commit, under the inſpection of the pooreſt Child.</p>
            <p>So that let the Hypocrite pretend never ſo much to believe, There is ſomething of Atheiſm in his Heart; for without that he might diſſemble with Men and Angels, but never du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> entertain one thought of prevaricating with his God, of putting ſuch tricks upon him, as <hi>Michol</hi> did upon <hi>Saul,</hi> of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding him with an Image, with a Puppet neatly dreſs'd, in-inſtead of a <hi>David,</hi> with a demure formal Saint in the place of a Man after his own Heart, and after his own Will.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:153296:9"/>
            <p>Certainly, this muſt be a Sin of the very firſt magnitude God is in Honour concern'd to vindicate Himſelf, to cut off the hopes of ſuch a wicked wretch, to make ſo daring a Sinner, a dreadful monument of his Fury and Indignation.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing our Hypocrite not Atheiſtically inclin'd, That he is no ſtranger to the Principles of Religion, that he believeth in his Heart, that God regardeth not the outward behaviour of any Man, when his inward parts are full of wickedneſs; and then let him tell me, what he thinks of his own condition, what ground he has to hope for the Mercy and Favour of God, with whom, he has dealt ſo baſely and unworthily. Will not his own Heart tell him, that his ſtate is as deſperate, as that of the looſeſt Libertine, will it not ſink within him at the approaches of Death. The very mention of Hell make him Startle, fancy himſelf already there, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine that he ſmells the Brimſtone and ſees the Flames flaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in his Face? and then what will become of all his hopes, will not his firſt Reflections on the place of Torments, fill him with black and melancholy Thoughts, and make his paſſage out of this Life very uneaſie and very uncomforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, vain are the hopes of the Hypocrite, and all his fair pretentions to the happineſs of another Life muſt fail and come to nothing, becauſe the Puniſhments, of a peculiar Tophet, are ordained of old, and prepar'd for him in the World to come.</p>
            <p>A Hypocrite among the Turks would willing compound for the eaſie pains of a Purgatory, for they believe that there are ſeven Caverns or Vaults in Hell, and aſſign the loweſt and hotteſt for all ſuch double Dealers and Diſſemblers; The Jews tell us that at the general Reſurrection, every body ſhall be forgiven, but Men of <hi>Gibeon;</hi> thoſe vile Hypocrites, who with their old clouted Shoes, and ragged Apparel impos'd upon their Governour <hi>Joſhua,</hi> But if we ſuſpect their Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, Chriſt himſelf aſſures us, He who cannot lye has told
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:153296:10"/>told us, that Hypocrites have a place of their own, a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that do's properly belong to them, where there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but weeping and gnaſhing of Teeth. He thunders out wo after wo againſt them, no leſs than eight times in the 23d Chapter of St. <hi>Matt.</hi> And if <hi>Pharo</hi>'s Dream was doubled unto him, to ſhew that the thing was Eſtabliſhed, and that God would ſurely bring it to paſs; may we not very well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that the Repetition of thoſe Woes againſt Hypocrites, beſpeaks the ſeverity of their future Puniſhments, and that the everlaſting Furnace ſhall be above ſeven times hotter for them, than for any other Tranſgreſſors. And indeed, it is but juſt with God to uſe them ſeverely, who have not dealt truly with Him. That they ſhould receive ſome ſpecial Mark of his juſt Reſentments and Diſpleaſure, that they ſhould for ever lye down in their ſhame and cover themſelves with their own Confuſion, that they and even all their better hopes ſhould unavoidably Periſh.</p>
            <p>And now as for the more particular hopes and expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our arbarous and inhumane Enemies, indeed they promis'd themſelves to do a very great and glorious Work, to kill and take poſſeſſion of all; To ſuppreſs our Religion, and Eſtabliſh their Idolatrous Worſhip, to wreſt the Sword out of his Majeſties Hands, to make themſelves abſolute Maſters of this Countrey and ſet up a King of their own; and when they were well fleſh'd and blooded, they made no doubt of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſporting<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their victorious Arms into <hi>England,</hi> of making that Kingdom ſuch another Shambles, and not leaving the Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of the Engliſh Name under Heaven.</p>
            <p>How far thoſe Inſtruments of Cruelty, might have prevail'd, to what a height they might have ſwell'd the Rivers of that Land too with blood, had not an over ruling Providence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpos'd and ſtay'd their hands, who in three Months had turn'd this Iſland of Saints into a Wilderneſs of ravening Woles; Murder'd and deſtroy'd an hundred and fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Souls, God knows.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:153296:10"/>
            <p>But bleſſed be his holy Name; Their hopes were in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great meaſure Bafled and Defeated, and we have yet a Gracious King, a Nurſing Father to the ſame Church, they then made ſuch Havock of, and Perſecuted with ſo much Rage and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. That Vine which Gods own Right Hand hath Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Flouriſhes in the Land, and after that excellent way which they ſtill call Hereſy; we even now Worſhip the God of our Fathers.</p>
            <p>And for thoſe great Incendiaries and Promoters of that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natural Rebellion, thoſe Blood thirſty and Deceitful Men, who would not that the Engliſh Monarchs ſhould Reign over them; Few of them liv'd out half their Days, or went down to their Graves in Peace, their Cruelties have been Repay'd unto their own Boſoms, as they have done, ſo God hath Rewarded them.</p>
            <p>And now if there be any Perſons here preſent, who perſiſt in the ſame Deſigns, act under the ſame Diſguiſes, and truly bear Witneſs, that they allow the Deeds of their Fathers, what can become of all their Hopes, either in this World or in that which is to come? God forbid that we ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe any Bounds to his Infinite Goodneſs and Mercy, but without true and unfeigned Repentance, we may without breach of Charity Conclude, That they who have been Saints only in ſhew, ſhall be ſav'd only in appearance, that their Expectations are all mere Notion; Their hopes a Golden Dream, and that they of all Men ſhall be moſt Miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>But let us who have better Principles be perſwaded to act honeſtly and ſincerely in all things, to let our Thoughts be always agreeable to our Words, our words conſiſtent with our actions, to retrieve again if poſſible, that plainneſs and openneſs of Heart, which a few years ago ſeemed to be the beſt part of our Tempers and Conſtitutions, to take care, that there be no ſecret Hipocriſy lurking in our Hearts, nothing of <hi>Judas</hi> his deſign, mixt with our concerns, for the poor of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:153296:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Jezebel</hi>'s with our Faſts, of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> with our long Prayers.</p>
            <p>An Hypocrite I told you ſignifi'd an Actor, or a Player, and now muſt ad, that the Play will ſhortly be done, and we muſt all take our leaves of the Stage for ever. A time will certainly come, when our Masks &amp; Veils ſhall be pull'd off, all our Habits and Diſguiſes laid aſide, and we ſhall have no more Cloaks for our Sin, but ſhall appear in our own Shapes and Colours, the ſame wicked Perſons; we were behind the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; and all our Iniquities ſhall be openly expos'd to the Eyes of God, Angels and Men.</p>
            <p>It will then be ſtrictly inquir'd, not how long we have Liv'd, but how Well, not in what Pomp and Splendor, but in what Religion and Devotion; not what Eſtates and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes we have left behind us, but what Souls and Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces we have brought along with us, and happy then ſhall we be: If we are able to ſay with good <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> Remember O Lord we beſeech thee, that we have walked before thee in Truth and with perfect Hearts; That ſo we may at the laſt hear the Muſick of that bleſſed Euge. Well done Good and Faithful Servants, enter you into the joy of your Maſter, <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
